<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-29T11:51:43-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Marcus Writes</title><subtitle>An intellectual-capital kaleidoscope</subtitle><entry><title type="html">On path choices, especially for rebels</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/which-road-to-take.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On path choices, especially for rebels" /><published>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/which-road-to-take</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/which-road-to-take.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-path-choices-especially-for-rebels">On path choices, especially for rebels</h1>

<p>Once, one of my closest friends referred to me in a blog post as “Reuben, the
rebel”. I was somewhat surprised, because this did not align with my self image
at that time. Not that I considered my views and actions to be normative.</p>

<p>I had definitely not consciously set out to be non-conforming. Instead, I was
trying to live by my values and world view, and I was keenly interested in
evolving my views. Over time, I could see that I was coming into some,
relatively minor friction with authority and would, as I saw it, stand my ground
on living how I thought is right. Even with all that I grew up pretty happily
and where my views differed from the mainstream view, I did not really suffer
any major consequences. Thus, never had a reason to think of myself as a rebel.</p>

<p>As my understanding of myself evolved, I have come to realize that my rational
decision making framework had a key trait. A higher, perhaps unreasonably high
weightage for adventure. In retrospect, however, I can see why my friend thought
of me as a rebel. Perhaps he saw me as making choices that were (sometimes
irrationally) rebellious?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On path choices, especially for rebels]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On attorney-client privilege</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/attorney-client-privilege.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On attorney-client privilege" /><published>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/attorney-client-privilege</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/attorney-client-privilege.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-attorney-client-privilege">On Attorney-client privilege</h1>
<p><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/justice">Justice</a> is the quality of being just or fair, as well as the maintenance of this quality.</p>

<p>A key factor in adjudicating what is fair or just, would be the ascertainment of truth. Even as some hold that truths <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Subjectivism">are subjective</a>, such subjective
truths even, if available to the adjudicator, would increase the odds of a fairer adjudication.</p>

<p><a href="https://thelawdictionary.org/article/what-is-attorney-client-privilege/">Attorney-client privilege</a> in simple terms renders
truths divulged to an attorney by a client to be inadmissible in court. This privilege allows a client, even when culpable, to be honest with the attorney, and for the attorney to advice the client on the optimal course of action. It increases the value added by the attorney. One downside might be that if the attorney is unscrupulous, it increases their leverage over the client. There is also the risk of unintended disclosure or leaks, which can be detrimental to the client’s interest even if the specific information is privileged and inadmissible in court since the opposite side, or an overzealous DA might use this information indirectly to uncover additional unfavorable evidence and such.</p>

<p>While the benefits to the client and the risks are somewhat clear, it is not clear how this privilege serves the interest of justice, since this might imposes a disadvantage to the opposite party. This effect is obviously more problematic in criminal trials, where there is a clear public interest. Further, given the adversarial nature of litigation, the sum of advantage to clients across all cases must be close to zero, and if weighted for the likelihood that it might be used for protecting the guilty more often than saving the innocent, it is negative.</p>

<p>Since the public, and a majority of the clients would only reap the adverse effects, one must wonder why this privilege continues. In
long running, yet seemingly irrational and unfair arrangements such as this, it is worthwhile to consider perverse incentives or conflicts of interest. Attorney-client privilege increase the value and leverage for lawyers, and this can translate to higher fees, at the minimum.</p>

<h3 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Buried bodies case</li>
  <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attorney%E2%80%93client_privilege">Wikipedia</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2039427">When States Demand Disclosure</a>
https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/History_of_the_legal_profession
https://online.law.tulane.edu/articles/law-in-the-ancient-world
https://judicature.duke.edu/articles/lawyers-the-legal-profession-access-to-justice-in-the-united-states-a-brief-history/</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Attorney-client privilege Justice is the quality of being just or fair, as well as the maintenance of this quality.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Risk tolerance and age</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/age-risk-tolerance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Risk tolerance and age" /><published>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/age-risk-tolerance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2023/02/01/age-risk-tolerance.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="risk-tolerance-and-age">Risk tolerance and age</h1>
<p>People, on the average, seem to grow more risk averse as they grow older, post early adulthood. While this certainly rang true anecdotally, further research agrees that this is indeed the case.</p>

<p>What could be the reasons for this? Could it be one or more of:<br />
- Waning physical abilities impact confidence<br />
- Societal expectations of maturity and associated behavior<br />
- Memory of previous failures<br />
- Adjustment, consciously or subconsciously, for slowing cellular regeneration rate<br />
- Brain anatomy changes, some of which are related to aging</p>

<p>Given my propensity for unconventional choices in life, and also recognizing that these choices sometimes worry my family and friends, I often think about the risk-return ratios of my choices. Risk, as used in conversational English, rather than  representing itself, likely represents the risk-return ratio, or maybe the risk adjusted returns. And risky choices or behaviour would be ones where one might have an expectation of a low return. Unconventional choices are perceived to have low or unknown risk-return ratio. I think I do have behavioral traits that make it more fun for me to make riskier choices. I</p>

<h2 id="additional-reading">Additional reading</h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5470073/">Stability and Change in Risk-Taking Propensity Across the Adult Lifespan</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms13822">Neuroanatomy accounts for age-related changes in risk preferences</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/identifying-effect-age-willingness-take-risks">https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/identifying-effect-age-willingness-take-risks</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ecca.12088">https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ecca.12088</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://scc.sa.utoronto.ca/content/genetics-of-risk-tolerance/">https://scc.sa.utoronto.ca/content/genetics-of-risk-tolerance/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.ucl.ac.uk/news/2016/dec/risk-avoidance-older-adults-related-brain-anatomy-not-age">https://www.ucl.ac.uk/news/2016/dec/risk-avoidance-older-adults-related-brain-anatomy-not-age</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Risk tolerance and age People, on the average, seem to grow more risk averse as they grow older, post early adulthood. While this certainly rang true anecdotally, further research agrees that this is indeed the case.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On knowledge asymmetry</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2021/02/01/knowledge-asymmetry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On knowledge asymmetry" /><published>2021-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2021/02/01/knowledge-asymmetry</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2021/02/01/knowledge-asymmetry.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="knowledge-asymmetry">Knowledge Asymmetry</h1>

<p>The most fundamental of inequities, the one that perpetuates all other inequities is information asymmetry, or more accurately, knowledge asymmetry. Almost any other inequity, whether in opportunity or outcome, could be mitigated if only the knowledge was available to the principal or a stakeholder, that the asymmetry existed; that solutions or in the absence thereof, coping mechanisms exist; that resources exist; somewhere, somehow. Further, the asymmetry is only resolved when this knowledge is delivered in a manner that allows the recipient to benefit from it - that is factoring in the knowledge delta and the trajectory from the subject’s current state of knowledge to the target state.</p>

<p>To put it succinctly, it is a complex problem that, if solved, could benefit humanity.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Knowledge Asymmetry]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Accessibility standards – destination or waypoint?</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/accessibility/2010/06/22/accessibility-standards-destination-or-waypoint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accessibility standards – destination or waypoint?" /><published>2010-06-22T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2010-06-22T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/accessibility/2010/06/22/accessibility-standards%E2%80%93destination-or-waypoint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/accessibility/2010/06/22/accessibility-standards-destination-or-waypoint.html"><![CDATA[<p>June 22, 2010 by Reuben
For the technology practitioner who works in the area of getting her solutions to work well for a diverse audience, there are a few related but often ambiguous terms that float around. Accessibility, usability, design …</p>

<p>For those of us who are particularly concerned about ensuring that web applications fit the needs of an audience with different faculties, there are a set of standards that are laid out that presumably will tell us how to do this. The question often comes up – is it worth the effort following standards like the W3C WCAG standard? There is a profusion of articles on the web that detail how standards compliance can be achieved and there are organizations who will help you, the web asset owner, get to standards compliance. What is often not that clear is the question of – what will WCAG compliance do for my users? How will my web asset benefit from this exercise? Does WCAG compliance mean that ALL users can use my web site ‘equitably’?</p>

<p>Focusing on the WCAG standard as an example, the standards body has stated that the goal of defining “how to make Web content more accessible to people with disabilities”. The standards body has decided, I believe consciously, to not precisely define accessibility. Also note the comparative term “more accessible” is chosen instead of a more absolute or superlative term. There is an air of tentativeness, which again, I would think, is a conscious choice.</p>

<p>There are a few more factors to consider:
Standards, in its final form often represent less than the state of the art in technology due to the long life cycle of the standards process itself. This is also clear from the facts that often even as a particular standard is in the stages of approval, work on the next standards commences. Standards bodies often need to come up with a least common denominator in its specification and in the interest of expediency, generally have to choose to ignore complicated or controversial issues.</p>

<p>Some of the issues related to accessibility, are so entwined in issues of usability and design, that it is difficult to make concrete standards without making assumptions about the nature of use of the system, the faculty set of the user and other environmental factors. In the continuum of accessibility-usability-design, the standards are only able to address the safe generalities than the highly variable specifics.</p>

<p>The points above should not be read as criticisms of standards, but merely as an observation of the facts.
Now, switching over to the practice side, take the classic cases where a web or digital asset owner takes the steps towards ensuring diversity. She is often driven by one or more of the following:
- <em>Social and values based reasons – CSR for companies, social pressure for individuals</em><br />
- I care about diversity, and want to make sure that there are no barriers in my organization for people with a non-standard set of faculties<br />
- I have a digital asset and want to come across to others as someone who cares about diversity
- <em>Regulatory and Legal</em><br />
- I need to comply to the accessibility rules/regulations/laws of my country/state/association in relation to and if I don’t there is a possible negative consequence<br />
- <em>Commercial</em><br />
- I or one of my customers have or will have an audience or customers that is diverse and needs accessibility
- I or one of my customers need to show some others that we are accessible so that we can get some new business
- I or one of my customers deal exclusively with a segment that have a non-standard set of faculties that have accessibility implications and our offering needs to be precisely tailored for them</p>

<p>Consider the various cases above. While clearly not an exhaustive treatment of all possible cases, you can see 2 significant flavors:
- I need to convince a certain constituency that my digital asset is accessible<br />
- I need to make my digital asset as accessible, usable and appropriate as possible to one or more specific class of users with non-standards faculties.</p>

<p>In both these cases, standards compliance is a requirement. For case 2 above, however, the asset owner would be ill-advised to stop at standards compliance and should consider additional steps to put forth the best possible offering – from accessibility, usability and design standpoints for the specific audience(s) in mind.</p>

<p>So here goes the stake in the ground:
We believe that standards compliance is a necessary but not sufficient condition for ensuring best possible levels of accessibility.
We do believe that current standards ensure a high degree of accessibility. However, we believe that there are additional steps that can and should be taken to allow a person with a non-standard set of faculties the best possible experience with a web site or application.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><category term="accessibility" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[June 22, 2010 by Reuben For the technology practitioner who works in the area of getting her solutions to work well for a diverse audience, there are a few related but often ambiguous terms that float around. Accessibility, usability, design …]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Experience blindness – a simulated screen reader experience for the sighted</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/screen%20reader/accessibility/2010/05/18/experience-blindness-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Experience blindness – a simulated screen reader experience for the sighted" /><published>2010-05-18T21:08:00-07:00</published><updated>2010-05-18T21:08:00-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/screen%20reader/accessibility/2010/05/18/experience-blindness-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/screen%20reader/accessibility/2010/05/18/experience-blindness-part-1.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="experience-blindness--a-simulated-screen-reader-experience-for-the-sighted">Experience blindness – a simulated screen reader experience for the sighted</h1>

<p>Ever wondered how a person with a visual impairment uses a computer? Surf the web? Read a book or an article? I know many people who shy away from asking these questions. The important thing is to realize that there’s no harm in asking these questions. The real harm is in not bothering to find the answers to these questions. A request to our visually impaired readers: please pass this article on to all your sighted friends. And dear sighted readers, walk with me through this simple simulation of the experience of a visually impaired person.</p>

<p>The most popular specialized software program used by people with visual impairments to consume electronic content – documents, web pages and other computer programs is a type of computer software known as a screen reader. The screen reader has two major functions – Navigation and Text-to-Speech (TTS). A screen reader aids in navigation by guiding the user in moving from one page to the other, from one paragraph to the other and so on. It aids in TTS by converting electronic text to sound – basically it reads out text. The biggest stumbling block for screen reader software are programs and content that is difficult for navigation.</p>

<p>A large majority of computer programs and electronic content that are used by the visually impaired, are created by sighted people – programmers, content writers, editors etc. If you happen to fall into this category of very powerful people, and if you are unfamiliar with screen readers, I would definitely encourage you to try this little experiment. Now, if you don’t, you might still want to do it – because it can open your eyes a little bit into an unfamiliar world. All you need is a computer, working eyes and an old newspaper.</p>

<p>Here you go:
- Turn on your computer<br />
- Browse to Google news or your favorite online haunt OR open a large word document<br />
- Now get an old newspaper – take one full sheet and open it up<br />
- Make a rectangular incision about 3 inches long and half inch wide at the center of the paper<br />
- With both hands, hold this newspaper against and in front of your computer display, so that you can see the screen through the rectangular hole<br />
- Now start reading through the hole. Move the paper to the right to continue reading<br />
- Try to jump to sections that you are interested in by moving the paper around<br />
- Read the whole page<br />
- Rinse and repeat with familiar and unfamiliar pages</p>

<p>Hope you enjoyed the experience :-)
Now we need some feedback from you:</p>

<p>How easy was it to find something that you are looking to read?
What would have made it easier to find what you were looking for?
Is the experience different between familiar and unfamiliar pages?
How would you change the design of your document/site/application after your experience of carrying out this experiment?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><category term="screen reader" /><category term="accessibility" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Experience blindness – a simulated screen reader experience for the sighted]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Universal Design</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2010/02/01/critique-universal-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Universal Design" /><published>2010-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2010-02-01T08:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2010/02/01/critique-universal-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/2010/02/01/critique-universal-design.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="on-universal-design">On Universal Design</h1>

<p>Universal Design as a concept was first proposed by Ronald Mace and recommends that all products and the built environment be designed to be aesthetic and usable to the greatest extent possible by everyone. There is a certain egalitarianism to
the idea, and as the drive towards greater inclusion accelerated, so did the belief that UD could be the panacea to solve
such issues. If only the designers would think of everyone as they design products, all would be well. This led to UD being prescribed broadly, either in conjunction with, or instead of, accessibility in the design of products and environments.</p>

<p>From a preliminary analysis, the “universal” part of universal design is almost always never achievable, without making the design so general that it works well for no one. Further, designers or the businesses that employ them are anyway incentivized by market forces to solve a problem such that they capture the largest market size. The challenges in</p>

<p>The premise that trying to make products that work amazingly well for people with differing faculties or faculty-sets is even feasible challenges common sense. In conclusion, in a large majority of design problems, universal design is not applicable, because the least common denominator design has little chance of success.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On Universal Design]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parable of the deviant rose</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/epistemology/learning/gratitude/2002/07/01/parable-of-the-deviant-rose.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parable of the deviant rose" /><published>2002-07-01T09:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2002-07-01T09:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/essays/epistemology/learning/gratitude/2002/07/01/parable-of-the-deviant-rose</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/essays/epistemology/learning/gratitude/2002/07/01/parable-of-the-deviant-rose.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="parable-of-the-deviant-rose">Parable of the deviant rose</h1>
<p>One hot afternoon, the master was in the mood for a discourse on the mysteries of life. “Is it wrong to take life”, he asked. A deep puff, a halo of smoke over his head, he set the plot as I looked on. “If it’s wrong to kill a cow”, said he, “is it wrong to kill a plant?. They say plants can’t feel. No?”. “But master”, said I, “plants have no pain - I have read, they have no nerves, they have no feelings”. The master looked at me and smiled, and then crushed out his cigarette. He rose and walked and I followed. The lair, full of smoke, shafts of sunlight streaking in.
He stepped into a small patch of weeds and shrubs. Solemnly he knelt and motioned me to do the same.
The rose with the dark red flowers stands next to a citrus plant. The leaves on the rose looked strange. They looked - lo and behold - like the leaves of the citrus. Somehow, by living near the citrus, the rose had become a little bit like the citrus.</p>

<p>“Sympathetic behavior”, the master announced. “And you say, plants have no pain, they can’t feel?”.
For just a moment, I had visions of screaming trees from Dahl’s Sound Machine.  With a twinkle in his eyes, he went on. “Rocks and trees and rivers, fish and cows and you. They are all alive - or all dead”.</p>
<hr />

<p>The late Dr. E Vijayan Nair was a professor in the Mechanical Engineering Department. He was brilliant and honest. He took some interest in me, probably seeing my tendency to not fall in line, and I am grateful to him for this. Of the little that I learnt in college, a good chunk came from this great teacher.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays" /><category term="epistemology" /><category term="learning" /><category term="gratitude" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Parable of the deviant rose One hot afternoon, the master was in the mood for a discourse on the mysteries of life. “Is it wrong to take life”, he asked. A deep puff, a halo of smoke over his head, he set the plot as I looked on. “If it’s wrong to kill a cow”, said he, “is it wrong to kill a plant?. They say plants can’t feel. No?”. “But master”, said I, “plants have no pain - I have read, they have no nerves, they have no feelings”. The master looked at me and smiled, and then crushed out his cigarette. He rose and walked and I followed. The lair, full of smoke, shafts of sunlight streaking in. He stepped into a small patch of weeds and shrubs. Solemnly he knelt and motioned me to do the same. The rose with the dark red flowers stands next to a citrus plant. The leaves on the rose looked strange. They looked - lo and behold - like the leaves of the citrus. Somehow, by living near the citrus, the rose had become a little bit like the citrus.]]></summary></entry></feed>