<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-08-29T12:00:16-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Marcus Writes</title><subtitle>An intellectual-capital kaleidoscope</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Genetic Engineering</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/2024/08/28/Genetic-Engineering.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Genetic Engineering" /><published>2024-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-08-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/2024/08/28/Genetic-Engineering</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/2024/08/28/Genetic-Engineering.html"><![CDATA[<p>Using recently discovered technologies, we can modify our own genetic code with staggering levels of precision, allowing us to do things we have never been able to before. <em>Genetic Engineering</em>, an article in the Gale library is one that goes over how genetic engineering, the science of changing the DNA of living organisms, works. People have been influencing the genes of organisms for thousands of years, using techniques like selective breeding and grafting to make living creatures inherit traits that are useful to us. Recently, we have come up with a more direct method: modifying the DNA of organisms directly by inserting segments of genetic code directly into the genome of animals. There are two main methods of this sort of modification: infecting the host organism with a hijacked virus that contains the desired gene, which leads to the virus planting the gene into the host, as in nature, viruses spread by inserting their genetic material into organisms . The second, more recent development is the use of the CRISPR-Cas9 protein (which will be referred to as CRISPR for the remainder of this essay), which is a tool derived from a bacterial defense against viruses, which in its original use case, cuts out the RNA of the virus once the virus attempts to infect the bacteria with its genetic code. When this protein is controlled in a lab setting, it allows the modification of genetic code with significantly more precision, since the protein used can be more finely manipulated. The use of CRISPR is met with much public opposition and is strictly regulated by many governments. Genetic engineering, especially in the form of CRISPR is a technology that has considerable potential to help cure disease, potential that doesn’t currently exist anywhere else. If regulators helped fund research into this technology, it could potentially allow numerous life saving medical treatments to be invented.<br />
In using this tool, the necessity of it becomes obvious. Its ability to permanently cure genetic disease is unmatched, because there are only the two existing methods of directly modifying genes: by using CRISPR, or by using a hijacked virus to deliver the gene into cells using the virus’ natural ability to insert its own genetic material into a host. A treatment for hemophilia, a genetic disorder that stops clotting, uses such a virus to implant the gene that fixes this disorder. This treatment vastly improves the quality of life of hemophiliacs, since they no longer have to fear scratches that would ordinarily be fatal.<br />
The use of CRISPR in medical treatment is a potent solution, a single intravenous infusion is all it takes to cure targeted ailments. In the right hands, it has the ability to alleviate significant human suffering. Sickle-cell anemia, a genetic disease that causes attacks where red blood cells clump up and tear, causing strokes and shortening life spans has recently had a cure discovered using CRISPR technology. With a single dose, people afflicted with the disease are cured. This treatment, Casgevy is causing many lives to be saved that would not ordinarily be, curing this disease and allowing people to live lives where they do not have to live in fear of dying of an attack.<br />
Now, while gene therapies are potent remedies, they are not without their drawbacks. Errors in implementation of these therapies, like the wrong genes being used, can cause unwanted mutations, or worse, cancers. Without careful identification and delivery of the donated gene, things can absolutely go awry. However, these side effects can and are being planned for before treatment. The FDA’s trial procedures are far beyond comprehensive enough to catch any side effects. It has taken 12 years of clinical trials for Casgevy to be cleared for human trials, the cost for the first three phases of the trials frequently exceeds the tens of millions, while the fourth often goes over the $50 million mark. With all of these measures in place, the pace of research has slowed down significantly, the high cost and time barriers making it hard for pharmaceutical companies to justify the investment without passing on the cost to the consumer. A dose of Casgevy costs $2.1 million. Of course, the patient is not often the one who pays, but insurance companies often try hard to find a way out of paying. If the government could help subsidize research into gene therapies, it is likely that the reduced cost of developing these treatments could increase the amount of people working on this, and therefore lead to more treatments.<br />
There is also the concern that the misuse of this technology could let people manipulate their genes to make themselves smarter, and give them the power to achieve world domination by using their superior intelligence. There are a couple of factors that keep this possibility from becoming probability. The technology’s cost is one, the multiple millions needed to fund a project of this scale would prevent someone from creating many of these Übermensch. Another is that there is currently no single gene that is associated with intelligence. Many researchers suggest there may be many genes responsible for intelligence, of which all are currently unknown to science. Finding the genes responsible is unlikely to be an easy endeavor. Finally, there have been shown to be links between higher IQ and certain mental disorders, meaning that it is possible that a superhumanly smart person might have mental illnesses that prevent them from functioning in society, which would probably make it difficult to take over the world.<br />
In sum, governmental funding of gene therapies is necessary because the potential benefits of this technology vastly outweigh its costs. There are many lives that could be saved or vastly improved in their quality, with fatal or chronic diseases, like genetic disorders and cancers potentially being curable with the use of this technology. The chances of you or a person that you know developing cancer in their lifetime is one in five. Helping researchers fund their cures could save the life of you or someone you know.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Using recently discovered technologies, we can modify our own genetic code with staggering levels of precision, allowing us to do things we have never been able to before. Genetic Engineering, an article in the Gale library is one that goes over how genetic engineering, the science of changing the DNA of living organisms, works. People have been influencing the genes of organisms for thousands of years, using techniques like selective breeding and grafting to make living creatures inherit traits that are useful to us. Recently, we have come up with a more direct method: modifying the DNA of organisms directly by inserting segments of genetic code directly into the genome of animals. There are two main methods of this sort of modification: infecting the host organism with a hijacked virus that contains the desired gene, which leads to the virus planting the gene into the host, as in nature, viruses spread by inserting their genetic material into organisms . The second, more recent development is the use of the CRISPR-Cas9 protein (which will be referred to as CRISPR for the remainder of this essay), which is a tool derived from a bacterial defense against viruses, which in its original use case, cuts out the RNA of the virus once the virus attempts to infect the bacteria with its genetic code. When this protein is controlled in a lab setting, it allows the modification of genetic code with significantly more precision, since the protein used can be more finely manipulated. The use of CRISPR is met with much public opposition and is strictly regulated by many governments. Genetic engineering, especially in the form of CRISPR is a technology that has considerable potential to help cure disease, potential that doesn’t currently exist anywhere else. If regulators helped fund research into this technology, it could potentially allow numerous life saving medical treatments to be invented. In using this tool, the necessity of it becomes obvious. Its ability to permanently cure genetic disease is unmatched, because there are only the two existing methods of directly modifying genes: by using CRISPR, or by using a hijacked virus to deliver the gene into cells using the virus’ natural ability to insert its own genetic material into a host. A treatment for hemophilia, a genetic disorder that stops clotting, uses such a virus to implant the gene that fixes this disorder. This treatment vastly improves the quality of life of hemophiliacs, since they no longer have to fear scratches that would ordinarily be fatal. The use of CRISPR in medical treatment is a potent solution, a single intravenous infusion is all it takes to cure targeted ailments. In the right hands, it has the ability to alleviate significant human suffering. Sickle-cell anemia, a genetic disease that causes attacks where red blood cells clump up and tear, causing strokes and shortening life spans has recently had a cure discovered using CRISPR technology. With a single dose, people afflicted with the disease are cured. This treatment, Casgevy is causing many lives to be saved that would not ordinarily be, curing this disease and allowing people to live lives where they do not have to live in fear of dying of an attack. Now, while gene therapies are potent remedies, they are not without their drawbacks. Errors in implementation of these therapies, like the wrong genes being used, can cause unwanted mutations, or worse, cancers. Without careful identification and delivery of the donated gene, things can absolutely go awry. However, these side effects can and are being planned for before treatment. The FDA’s trial procedures are far beyond comprehensive enough to catch any side effects. It has taken 12 years of clinical trials for Casgevy to be cleared for human trials, the cost for the first three phases of the trials frequently exceeds the tens of millions, while the fourth often goes over the $50 million mark. With all of these measures in place, the pace of research has slowed down significantly, the high cost and time barriers making it hard for pharmaceutical companies to justify the investment without passing on the cost to the consumer. A dose of Casgevy costs $2.1 million. Of course, the patient is not often the one who pays, but insurance companies often try hard to find a way out of paying. If the government could help subsidize research into gene therapies, it is likely that the reduced cost of developing these treatments could increase the amount of people working on this, and therefore lead to more treatments. There is also the concern that the misuse of this technology could let people manipulate their genes to make themselves smarter, and give them the power to achieve world domination by using their superior intelligence. There are a couple of factors that keep this possibility from becoming probability. The technology’s cost is one, the multiple millions needed to fund a project of this scale would prevent someone from creating many of these Übermensch. Another is that there is currently no single gene that is associated with intelligence. Many researchers suggest there may be many genes responsible for intelligence, of which all are currently unknown to science. Finding the genes responsible is unlikely to be an easy endeavor. Finally, there have been shown to be links between higher IQ and certain mental disorders, meaning that it is possible that a superhumanly smart person might have mental illnesses that prevent them from functioning in society, which would probably make it difficult to take over the world. In sum, governmental funding of gene therapies is necessary because the potential benefits of this technology vastly outweigh its costs. There are many lives that could be saved or vastly improved in their quality, with fatal or chronic diseases, like genetic disorders and cancers potentially being curable with the use of this technology. The chances of you or a person that you know developing cancer in their lifetime is one in five. Helping researchers fund their cures could save the life of you or someone you know.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Analysis of Le Guin’s Omelas</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Analysis-of-Le-Guin's-Omelas.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Analysis of Le Guin’s Omelas" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Analysis-of-Le-Guin&apos;s-Omelas</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Analysis-of-Le-Guin&apos;s-Omelas.html"><![CDATA[<p>Why do we turn a blind eye to the injustice around us? Ursula Le Guin, an award-winning author in her story <em>The Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas</em> tells a harrowing tale about a city called Omelas, an idyllic place where children dance, people live in happiness, and the harvest is bountiful. The only thing is, one inhabitant of Omelas keeps this paradise together. They live in a little basement room under one of the quaint little houses. They are a little child, and they are trapped in this place, as they are starved, neglected, and tortured. The misery that this child – who has never seen the light of day – feels, is necessary for the rest of Omelas to exist. There can be no paradise without it. The people of Omelas know about this child, and while some choose to leave the town, and some actively hurt the child, most choose to stay, knowing about this atrocity. What this shows is that The Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas is a story that uses this symbolism, of the child in the basement to represent how people in the real world behave when they are exposed to injustice in their society.<br />
	The people that live in the city knowing about the child, represent how people can ignore injustice in their communities if it serves their own interests. In Omelas, a majority of the population go about their lives and enjoy their paradise, even knowing about the child. In the real world, the period where slavery was prevalent indicates a similar thought process: that the freedoms of the enslaved are of no consequence when compared with the comfort afforded by it. There is a passage that states, “they all know it is there, all the people of Omelas. Some of them have come to see it, others are content merely to know it is there. They all know that it has to be there.” (Le Guin 5) The entire community, the gaily dancing children, the citizens that enjoy the festivals and plentiful harvests are all complicit in the suffering of the child in the basement. They live their lives, enjoying themselves even with this knowledge. This shows a specific apathy, one that allows them to let this child suffer if they believe it to work to keep the city a paradise. This is a stark parallel to how injustices are accepted in the real world for the sake of personal comfort. Around the world, there are places where precious metals are mined. Cramped, unstable, and dangerous mineshafts. In the Congo, these places are built to extract and sell cobalt, which is used to process crude oil. The people that work in these mines are more often than not people from the local villages, some of whom are children, all of whom are taken advantage of. People in places that use the refined oil don’t often think of what it costs to get it, but use it regardless. This is just one example of the kind of outrage that occurs every day, and <em>Omelas</em> paints a vivid picture of it.<br />
	One more unsettling part of the story is where the Omelasians who abuse the child take advantage of the existing injustice to cause further harm. They see injustice in their community and desire to be a part of it. This represents how when given the opportunity, people in communities with broken components take advantage to cause further harm. This is detailed in the story: “Sometimes the door rattles terribly and opens, and a person, or several people, are there. One of them may come and kick the child to make it stand up. The others never come close, but peer in at it with frightened, disgusted eyes.” (Le Guin 5) These Omelasians who come into the child’s room see this injustice with their own eyes, they see the pain that the child feels, and yet they perpetuate the practice. They are abusive, neglectful, and they hurt the child, because they have an excuse to inflict pain on a person. This is mirrored in the real world by ‘spineless sadists’, those that use the power granted to them by laws and common practices to cause harm.<br />
	The people that choose to leave Omelas, represent how when some people see injustice in their communities, they refuse to participate in it, and reject the institution. These people are described as such: “at times one of the adolescent girls or boys who go to see the child does not go home to weep or rage, does not, in fact, go home at all. Sometimes also a man or woman<br />
much older falls silent for a day or two, and then leaves home.” (Le Guin 6) These other Omelasians see injustice enmeshed with their community, and refuse to be a part of it. They reject the institution, and therefore their community which is founded on that institution. This is paralleled in the real world by conscientious objectors: people who refuse to take part in wars that their governments wage, often creating friction between themselves and their communities. Famously, during the Vietnam war, people all over the United States got together to decry the war. They refused to leave and fight, they refused to participate in the injustice that they saw happening right in front of their eyes.<br />
	Some might say that it might be better to work in the interest of the greater good and let the child suffer for the benefit of the rest of the population, and that the suffering of one child is inconsequential when compared to the enormous benefit to the population. The people of Omelas are happy and healthy, and to let just one child suffer for all this good is the kinder thing to do for the population. However, even if it is better for more people for one child to suffer, that does not erase the cruelty to the child, an innocent. How can anything good be based on a practice of such cruelty? Omelas, and the happiness it entails are all tainted by this one cruelty. Every child’s smile as they play, every excited conversation between friends, all of it is warped because of this part of the society that the Omelasians subscribe to.<br />
Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas tells the story of a society that has a deeply embedded transgression, and the different reactions of its people to the child in the basement represents this as an analogue to how people are affected by societal wrongs that are deeply rooted in their communities. You would be hard pressed to find a country that hasn’t had some event in their history that its people deeply regret. We can’t pretend the parts that are wrong in our societies don’t exist, but we have the power to institute change, and try to make it right. Doing what’s right is rarely comfortable. In order to correct the flaws in the systems around us, we need to be prepared for discomfort so we can enact real, positive change.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why do we turn a blind eye to the injustice around us? Ursula Le Guin, an award-winning author in her story The Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas tells a harrowing tale about a city called Omelas, an idyllic place where children dance, people live in happiness, and the harvest is bountiful. The only thing is, one inhabitant of Omelas keeps this paradise together. They live in a little basement room under one of the quaint little houses. They are a little child, and they are trapped in this place, as they are starved, neglected, and tortured. The misery that this child – who has never seen the light of day – feels, is necessary for the rest of Omelas to exist. There can be no paradise without it. The people of Omelas know about this child, and while some choose to leave the town, and some actively hurt the child, most choose to stay, knowing about this atrocity. What this shows is that The Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas is a story that uses this symbolism, of the child in the basement to represent how people in the real world behave when they are exposed to injustice in their society. The people that live in the city knowing about the child, represent how people can ignore injustice in their communities if it serves their own interests. In Omelas, a majority of the population go about their lives and enjoy their paradise, even knowing about the child. In the real world, the period where slavery was prevalent indicates a similar thought process: that the freedoms of the enslaved are of no consequence when compared with the comfort afforded by it. There is a passage that states, “they all know it is there, all the people of Omelas. Some of them have come to see it, others are content merely to know it is there. They all know that it has to be there.” (Le Guin 5) The entire community, the gaily dancing children, the citizens that enjoy the festivals and plentiful harvests are all complicit in the suffering of the child in the basement. They live their lives, enjoying themselves even with this knowledge. This shows a specific apathy, one that allows them to let this child suffer if they believe it to work to keep the city a paradise. This is a stark parallel to how injustices are accepted in the real world for the sake of personal comfort. Around the world, there are places where precious metals are mined. Cramped, unstable, and dangerous mineshafts. In the Congo, these places are built to extract and sell cobalt, which is used to process crude oil. The people that work in these mines are more often than not people from the local villages, some of whom are children, all of whom are taken advantage of. People in places that use the refined oil don’t often think of what it costs to get it, but use it regardless. This is just one example of the kind of outrage that occurs every day, and Omelas paints a vivid picture of it. One more unsettling part of the story is where the Omelasians who abuse the child take advantage of the existing injustice to cause further harm. They see injustice in their community and desire to be a part of it. This represents how when given the opportunity, people in communities with broken components take advantage to cause further harm. This is detailed in the story: “Sometimes the door rattles terribly and opens, and a person, or several people, are there. One of them may come and kick the child to make it stand up. The others never come close, but peer in at it with frightened, disgusted eyes.” (Le Guin 5) These Omelasians who come into the child’s room see this injustice with their own eyes, they see the pain that the child feels, and yet they perpetuate the practice. They are abusive, neglectful, and they hurt the child, because they have an excuse to inflict pain on a person. This is mirrored in the real world by ‘spineless sadists’, those that use the power granted to them by laws and common practices to cause harm. The people that choose to leave Omelas, represent how when some people see injustice in their communities, they refuse to participate in it, and reject the institution. These people are described as such: “at times one of the adolescent girls or boys who go to see the child does not go home to weep or rage, does not, in fact, go home at all. Sometimes also a man or woman much older falls silent for a day or two, and then leaves home.” (Le Guin 6) These other Omelasians see injustice enmeshed with their community, and refuse to be a part of it. They reject the institution, and therefore their community which is founded on that institution. This is paralleled in the real world by conscientious objectors: people who refuse to take part in wars that their governments wage, often creating friction between themselves and their communities. Famously, during the Vietnam war, people all over the United States got together to decry the war. They refused to leave and fight, they refused to participate in the injustice that they saw happening right in front of their eyes. Some might say that it might be better to work in the interest of the greater good and let the child suffer for the benefit of the rest of the population, and that the suffering of one child is inconsequential when compared to the enormous benefit to the population. The people of Omelas are happy and healthy, and to let just one child suffer for all this good is the kinder thing to do for the population. However, even if it is better for more people for one child to suffer, that does not erase the cruelty to the child, an innocent. How can anything good be based on a practice of such cruelty? Omelas, and the happiness it entails are all tainted by this one cruelty. Every child’s smile as they play, every excited conversation between friends, all of it is warped because of this part of the society that the Omelasians subscribe to. Ones Who Walk Away From Omelas tells the story of a society that has a deeply embedded transgression, and the different reactions of its people to the child in the basement represents this as an analogue to how people are affected by societal wrongs that are deeply rooted in their communities. You would be hard pressed to find a country that hasn’t had some event in their history that its people deeply regret. We can’t pretend the parts that are wrong in our societies don’t exist, but we have the power to institute change, and try to make it right. Doing what’s right is rarely comfortable. In order to correct the flaws in the systems around us, we need to be prepared for discomfort so we can enact real, positive change.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Diving into ‘Diving into the Wreck’</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Diving-into-'Diving-into-the-Wreck'.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diving into ‘Diving into the Wreck’" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Diving-into-&apos;Diving-into-the-Wreck&apos;</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Diving-into-&apos;Diving-into-the-Wreck&apos;.html"><![CDATA[<p>“We are, I am, you are<br />
by cowardice or courage<br />
the one who find our way<br />
back to this scene<br />
carrying a knife, a camera<br />
a book of myths<br />
in which<br />
our names do not appear.”<br />
-Adrienne Rich, <em>Diving into the Wreck</em></p>

<p>In the poem <em>Diving into the Wreck,</em> Adrienne Rich inserts a lot of symbolism beneath the surface. It explores an almost ethereal experience underwater, that leaves much unanswered. The poem’s writer, Adrienne Rich, is a Harvard graduate, the receiver of the Gugenheim fellowship, and is also a highly impactful activist. The poem describes someone diving under the ocean and finding a shipwreck which they then explore. There is rich, yet abstract description of the experiences of the diver, like in donning equipment, the descent into the depths of the ocean, and in entering the shipwreck. The poem is quite interesting because the way in which it is composed makes it good for interpretation, and it seems to be pointing the reader in a specific direction. <em>Diving into the wreck</em> is a poem that uses the symbols of an undersea dive and the exploration of a shipwreck to represent death in its forms as a lonely, inevitable journey.<br />
	The time before the dive under the water symbolizes the lonely journey towards death. When Rich writes about the time before the dive, she says: “There is a ladder. The ladder is always there hanging innocently close to the side of the schooner. We know what it is for, we who have used it.” (Rich, second stanza) This ladder is a symbol that represents the popular personification of death, a figure that creeps ever close. The attention paid to the constant proximity of this ladder echoes how death is ever present and inescapable. Those close to death are being referred to as “[those] who have used it” as they know that as they approach death, the knowledge of the ladder parallels the knowledge of the final destination is revealed. The attention paid to the constant proximity of this ladder echoes how death is ever present and inescapable.<br />
The passage where the diver enters the shipwreck deems to heavily use imagery of rotting and failing components. This is emblematic of the physical state of death. In this passage, as we dive into the wreck, this parts sticks out: “I am she: I am he / whose drowned face sleeps with open eyes / whose breasts still bear the stress.” It begins by calling attention to a figure that is both male and female. This represents how death comes for all of us, men and women alike. The next, the open eyed sleeper who still bears stress, is a seemingly contrasting image, but the first part is emblematic of the final, eternal sleep following death, while the second symbolizes regret in death.<br />
	From another perspective, the poem could also be interpreted as a journey of self-discovery by using the actual dive to metaphorically dive into one’s identity. Erykah Matabang in the week five discussion argues that the poem portrays the inner struggles and challenges faced by people as they seek to understand themselves and their place in the world. It highlights one person’s lonely descent fraught with uncertainty, obstacles and revelations as a metaphor for self-discovery. The poem could be saying that the path toward self-discovery is long and arduous, and can involve facing harsh truths about oneself. The description of donning “body-armor of black rubber,” “absurd flippers,” and a “grave and awkward mask” (Rich, Stanza 1) symbolizes the protective barriers individuals may erect as they embark on the journey of self-exploration. Despite the challenges and discomfort, the speaker persists in their quest to explore the wreck, representing the determination and courage required to delve into one’s own depths and confront the complexities of identity.<br />
	While there is certainly room to accept another interpretation of a work of art, what is missing in Erykah’s analysis is that Rich wrote the poem shortly following the suicide of her husband. This close time frame would make it unlikely that her writings in the period following were not influenced by this major event. Rich was also participating in anti-war demonstrations close to this time, another event that could bring death to the forefront of her creative mind.<br />
	Rich’s poem is inundated with hidden meaning, and there is certainly a lot to explore within it. Its colorful yet ethereal descriptions of the journey our diver takes leaves the reader with a sense that they have left with something intangible. Its frequent use of allegory to bring the mind toward the idea of death is impressive, and is a curious look into the mind of Rich after the events that uprooted her life. Understanding how events like this affect us is vital to learning more about ourselves. Maybe we should all consider using art as a medium to express how we feel, and what we think.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“We are, I am, you are by cowardice or courage the one who find our way back to this scene carrying a knife, a camera a book of myths in which our names do not appear.” -Adrienne Rich, Diving into the Wreck]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Loneliness</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Loneliness.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Loneliness" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Loneliness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Loneliness.html"><![CDATA[<p>Loneliness is said to be an epidemic, but it isn’t often shown how this epidemic affects people like a true plague. Heart disease, stroke, hypertension. People who face loneliness often face significantly increased rates of these diseases. Loneliness worldwide is skyrocketing, and so too do the occurrences of cardiovascular, mental and other illnesses. People have grappled with loneliness and the problems it causes for hundreds of years. Recently, as the problem of societal loneliness has taken the public stage, there have been government campaigns spreading awareness and spearheading solutions. However, epidemic loneliness is still a dangerously prevalent problem that has yet to be solved. Still, the issues it creates are not so unconquerable. The diseases that it contributes to, the anxieties it feeds, while these are debilitating afflictions, there are proven and effective treatments for these offshoot problems loneliness spawns. By focusing on individualized treatments for these splinter pathologies loneliness creates, the core problem can be weakened and dismantled.<br />
The increasing levels of loneliness across the globe can grant opportunities for other diseases to take root and cause harm. According to Louise Hawkley, a columnist in the <em>Nature</em> journal,  “In one meta-analysis of 70 studies, individuals who were lonely had 26% greater odds of early mortality than non-lonely individuals.” What this shows is that loneliness is extremely dangerous business. This issue that is ingrained in our societies is causing too much damage to the population, especially to more vulnerable demographics, like the adolescent and elderly population, as supported by Hawkley’s analysis, where she states “…the frequency of loneliness…is highest in young adulthood, declines in middle adulthood and early old age, and then increases into oldest old age.” The most vulnerable members of our population are the most susceptible to the core issue of loneliness and the diseases it causes, which run rampant in their bodies.<br />
	Loneliness is an especially dangerous condition in younger people. Children and young adults need social engagement as part of their development, and loneliness can have an exacerbated negative effect on their mental growth. According to “Loneliness as a health issue”, an article in the <em>Lancet</em>, a reputed medical journal, “adolescents and young adults, for whom socialization is such a key part of development, could be particularly vulnerable, with potentially long-term consequences for mental and physical wellbeing.” What this means is that if we want to keep our young population safe from this danger, we need decisive and precise intervention, and there is little time to waste. The long-term effects of loneliness on the development of children aren’t known, and we cannot in good conscience continue on our current path, endangering future generations.<br />
Loneliness is a complex issue that is yet to be solved. Instead of tackling the core of the issue head on, focusing on the issues loneliness creates can be a more achievable goal that can help more people in the long run. Dora Hopf, a <em>Nature</em> columnist, in her article ”Loneliness and diurnal cortisol levels” states, “in adolescents, significant correlations between self-reported loneliness and cortisol awakening responses during COVID-19 lockdown were found.” What this means is that the levels of cortisol, the hormone that regulates stress, are increased in people that feel lonely. This means that there is a correlation between stress and loneliness. Now, if this stress can be mitigated, this harmful aspect of loneliness can be eliminated, thereby making loneliness safer. According to the Mayo Clinic, “Almost any form of exercise or movement can increase your fitness level while decreasing your stress.” Stress borne from loneliness can be mitigated by exercise, it would make sense that this can be applied similarly to other problems loneliness causes. While this idea of disarming loneliness by fixing some of the smaller issues it causes has not been explored much yet, it can control some of the dangers inherent to loneliness.<br />
Critics could say that the correlation between loneliness and these pathologies does not necessarily imply causation: people who are afflicted by these conditions could become lonely due to the disease making them draw away from social situations rather than the other way around. There might not even be a connection between the two, the two variables could be completely unrelated. However, the other side is that with a topic as well studied as loneliness, it is unlikely that the multitude of people looking for a link between loneliness and disease are making the same error. If it was just a few isolated studies that show a correlation between loneliness and disease, that argument could be valid. However, the majority of studies that ask this question conclude that loneliness causes disease. Even though mixing up correlation and causation is an easy fallacy to fall into, when there is overwhelming evidence to the contrary, like in the case of the relationship that loneliness has with disease, the link between them becomes clear.<br />
There is also the opposing stance that in writing loneliness off as too hard to fix and attempting to fix it by mitigating its dangers that aren’t the core issue, we do not fix the actual loneliness epidemic. Admittedly, it is true that the root issue is not solved, loneliness will still exist even if its harmful effects are mitigated. Even if better support systems are put into place for people facing second-order issues caused by loneliness, human solutions are fallible. Neglecting the root problem could lead to problems slipping through the cracks, and so there could still be harm done to people. However, any improvement made in the battle against loneliness is a step in the right direction. While putting resources into helping people facing secondary symptoms of loneliness does not solve the root issue, it still helps people. There’s also the angle that fixing the secondary problems loneliness causes is a much easier solution to implement than directly trying to fix the loneliness epidemic. Institutions may get more value for the resource investment they put in, and therefore help more people by putting resources into sorting out the secondary problems caused by loneliness rather than loneliness itself. It could be a safer choice to prioritize expending resources on issues we know how to fix rather than trying to come up with new solutions to the pervasive issue of loneliness, for now at least. Going back to the case of exercise as a treatment for loneliness, incentivizing people to exercise would be a good step in combating loneliness. Incentivizing exercise is not easy, governments have been trying to get people to regularly exercise for a while, with varying levels of success. Developing foundations in routine exercise or participating in exercise programs might be a more achievable goal. One possible strategy based on this idea is to encourage participation in  exercise programs such as the first phase of military basic training, by giving out tax breaks. Basic training at the lowest level largely consists of physical training and first aid. It would be easy for the government to track completion and dispense tax breaks accordingly, and the physical workload would help build a starting point for people to launch off of to begin routinely exercising. This is one way that loneliness can be treated by managing a splinter pathology caused by the root problem. Creating incentives and programs that address these splinter pathologies can provide tangible and effective results as we work to tackle the loneliness that is ingrained in society.<br />
To put it briefly, loneliness is an issue that is prevalent in today’s society and is causing harm in indirect ways, like mental and physical illness. While loneliness is a complex problem, it isn’t a problem that we can’t work to mitigate. Reducing the harm loneliness can potentially cause by using supportive interventions on the smaller issues it creates is a strategy that is easier to implement, and it can be impactful at individual and institutional levels. Thinking about complex issues like loneliness in a manner that lets us take smaller steps toward solving them could help us find solutions to them in more achievable ways.</p>

<p>Works Cited<br />
Hawkley, L.C. Loneliness and health. Nat Rev Dis Primers 8, 22 (2022)<br />
The Lancet. “Loneliness as a Health Issue.” <em>The Lancet</em>, vol. 402, no. 10396, 1 July 2023, pp. 79–79<br />
Mayo Clinic . “Exercise and Stress: Get Moving to Manage Stress.” Mayo Clinic, 3 Aug. 2022<br />
Hopf, Dora, et al. “Loneliness and Diurnal Cortisol Levels during COVID-19 Lockdown: The Roles of Living Situation, Relationship Status and Relationship Quality.” Scientific Reports, vol. 12, no. 1, 5 Sept. 2022</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Loneliness is said to be an epidemic, but it isn’t often shown how this epidemic affects people like a true plague. Heart disease, stroke, hypertension. People who face loneliness often face significantly increased rates of these diseases. Loneliness worldwide is skyrocketing, and so too do the occurrences of cardiovascular, mental and other illnesses. People have grappled with loneliness and the problems it causes for hundreds of years. Recently, as the problem of societal loneliness has taken the public stage, there have been government campaigns spreading awareness and spearheading solutions. However, epidemic loneliness is still a dangerously prevalent problem that has yet to be solved. Still, the issues it creates are not so unconquerable. The diseases that it contributes to, the anxieties it feeds, while these are debilitating afflictions, there are proven and effective treatments for these offshoot problems loneliness spawns. By focusing on individualized treatments for these splinter pathologies loneliness creates, the core problem can be weakened and dismantled. The increasing levels of loneliness across the globe can grant opportunities for other diseases to take root and cause harm. According to Louise Hawkley, a columnist in the Nature journal, “In one meta-analysis of 70 studies, individuals who were lonely had 26% greater odds of early mortality than non-lonely individuals.” What this shows is that loneliness is extremely dangerous business. This issue that is ingrained in our societies is causing too much damage to the population, especially to more vulnerable demographics, like the adolescent and elderly population, as supported by Hawkley’s analysis, where she states “…the frequency of loneliness…is highest in young adulthood, declines in middle adulthood and early old age, and then increases into oldest old age.” The most vulnerable members of our population are the most susceptible to the core issue of loneliness and the diseases it causes, which run rampant in their bodies. Loneliness is an especially dangerous condition in younger people. Children and young adults need social engagement as part of their development, and loneliness can have an exacerbated negative effect on their mental growth. According to “Loneliness as a health issue”, an article in the Lancet, a reputed medical journal, “adolescents and young adults, for whom socialization is such a key part of development, could be particularly vulnerable, with potentially long-term consequences for mental and physical wellbeing.” What this means is that if we want to keep our young population safe from this danger, we need decisive and precise intervention, and there is little time to waste. The long-term effects of loneliness on the development of children aren’t known, and we cannot in good conscience continue on our current path, endangering future generations. Loneliness is a complex issue that is yet to be solved. Instead of tackling the core of the issue head on, focusing on the issues loneliness creates can be a more achievable goal that can help more people in the long run. Dora Hopf, a Nature columnist, in her article ”Loneliness and diurnal cortisol levels” states, “in adolescents, significant correlations between self-reported loneliness and cortisol awakening responses during COVID-19 lockdown were found.” What this means is that the levels of cortisol, the hormone that regulates stress, are increased in people that feel lonely. This means that there is a correlation between stress and loneliness. Now, if this stress can be mitigated, this harmful aspect of loneliness can be eliminated, thereby making loneliness safer. According to the Mayo Clinic, “Almost any form of exercise or movement can increase your fitness level while decreasing your stress.” Stress borne from loneliness can be mitigated by exercise, it would make sense that this can be applied similarly to other problems loneliness causes. While this idea of disarming loneliness by fixing some of the smaller issues it causes has not been explored much yet, it can control some of the dangers inherent to loneliness. Critics could say that the correlation between loneliness and these pathologies does not necessarily imply causation: people who are afflicted by these conditions could become lonely due to the disease making them draw away from social situations rather than the other way around. There might not even be a connection between the two, the two variables could be completely unrelated. However, the other side is that with a topic as well studied as loneliness, it is unlikely that the multitude of people looking for a link between loneliness and disease are making the same error. If it was just a few isolated studies that show a correlation between loneliness and disease, that argument could be valid. However, the majority of studies that ask this question conclude that loneliness causes disease. Even though mixing up correlation and causation is an easy fallacy to fall into, when there is overwhelming evidence to the contrary, like in the case of the relationship that loneliness has with disease, the link between them becomes clear. There is also the opposing stance that in writing loneliness off as too hard to fix and attempting to fix it by mitigating its dangers that aren’t the core issue, we do not fix the actual loneliness epidemic. Admittedly, it is true that the root issue is not solved, loneliness will still exist even if its harmful effects are mitigated. Even if better support systems are put into place for people facing second-order issues caused by loneliness, human solutions are fallible. Neglecting the root problem could lead to problems slipping through the cracks, and so there could still be harm done to people. However, any improvement made in the battle against loneliness is a step in the right direction. While putting resources into helping people facing secondary symptoms of loneliness does not solve the root issue, it still helps people. There’s also the angle that fixing the secondary problems loneliness causes is a much easier solution to implement than directly trying to fix the loneliness epidemic. Institutions may get more value for the resource investment they put in, and therefore help more people by putting resources into sorting out the secondary problems caused by loneliness rather than loneliness itself. It could be a safer choice to prioritize expending resources on issues we know how to fix rather than trying to come up with new solutions to the pervasive issue of loneliness, for now at least. Going back to the case of exercise as a treatment for loneliness, incentivizing people to exercise would be a good step in combating loneliness. Incentivizing exercise is not easy, governments have been trying to get people to regularly exercise for a while, with varying levels of success. Developing foundations in routine exercise or participating in exercise programs might be a more achievable goal. One possible strategy based on this idea is to encourage participation in exercise programs such as the first phase of military basic training, by giving out tax breaks. Basic training at the lowest level largely consists of physical training and first aid. It would be easy for the government to track completion and dispense tax breaks accordingly, and the physical workload would help build a starting point for people to launch off of to begin routinely exercising. This is one way that loneliness can be treated by managing a splinter pathology caused by the root problem. Creating incentives and programs that address these splinter pathologies can provide tangible and effective results as we work to tackle the loneliness that is ingrained in society. To put it briefly, loneliness is an issue that is prevalent in today’s society and is causing harm in indirect ways, like mental and physical illness. While loneliness is a complex problem, it isn’t a problem that we can’t work to mitigate. Reducing the harm loneliness can potentially cause by using supportive interventions on the smaller issues it creates is a strategy that is easier to implement, and it can be impactful at individual and institutional levels. Thinking about complex issues like loneliness in a manner that lets us take smaller steps toward solving them could help us find solutions to them in more achievable ways.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sula Analysis</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Sula-Analysis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sula Analysis" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Sula-Analysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/Sula-Analysis.html"><![CDATA[<p>The kind of books that stick with people are the compelling ones. For a story to command its reader’s attention and become a fond memory, it needs to tell a story with characters that feel alive. A book that is considered successful, with characters that function in this way can be said to have good characterization. Successful characterization in fiction can make the reading experience a personal one. To the individual, literature that becomes successful like this can turn into a portal into any time, and the individual can embed themselves into a fictional world. Stories like Wonder and Moby have this ability, they let the individual experience the story alongside the characters through their vivid depictions.<br />
<em>Sula</em> follows the life of Sula Peace, a girl who lives with her mother, grandmother, and several adopted family members in The Bottom, a relatively poor neighborhood. The story takes the reader through the life of her and some of the other members of The Bottom, eventually culminating in Sula’s staunchly different worldview leading her to become alienated from her community, and ending in her death. The rich characterization of the characters in <em>Sula</em>, whether they are Sula herself or other less prominent characters such as Jude, is what makes the story successful.<br />
In <em>Sula</em>, the character of Jude is part of what makes the book successful because of how relatable his yearning for purpose and meaningful work is. Jude works as a hotel waiter, but he craves meaningful work, and a legacy. In a passage where he has the chance to work on building a bridge, he reveals his motivations: “Jude himself longed more than anybody else to be taken. Not just for the good money, more for the work itself… His arms ached for something heavier than trays, for something dirtier than peelings; his feet wanted the heavy work shoes, not the thin-soled black shoes that the hotel required” (Morrison 92). Jude has a desire to do something other than the job he sustains himself with. The dissatisfaction with his hotel job that he feels is a common experience to a lot of people, and this desire he has makes him relatable to the reader. Jude also expresses a desire to have accomplished something that lasts long after he is gone, and this want for a legacy is also potentially relatable at the personal level to many readers, which is likely to interest readers. Jude feels that, “More than anything he wanted the camaraderie of the road men: the lunch buckets, the hollering, the body movement that in the end produced something real, something he could point to. “I built that road,” he could say. How much better sundown would be than the end of a day in the restaurant, where a good day’s work was marked by the number of dirty plates and the weight of the garbage bin. “I built that road.” People would walk over his sweat for years” (Morrison 92). Speaking for myself at least, I think that I share Jude’s desire to put something into the world that people can benefit from for many years to come. The reason that Jude’s motivations and desires are the sort that can be found in people in general is due to precise and insightful characterization, and this is why <em>Sula</em> is a memorable and successful piece of literature.<br />
The characterization of the title character of the story, Sula, is a key element in making the book the work of art that it is. The starkly alien perspective that Sula is shown to hold forces the reader to attempt putting themselves in Sula’s shoes, and to try and understand this strange person’s actions. Towards the end of the story, this perspective is shown: <br />
She had no thought at all of causing Nel pain when she bedded down with Jude. They had always shared the affection of other people: compared how a boy kissed, what line he used with one and then the other. Marriage, apparently, had changed all that, but having had no intimate knowledge of marriage, having lived in a house with women who thought all men available, and selected from among them with a care only for their tastes, she was ill prepared for the possessiveness of the one person she felt close to. She knew well enough what other women said and felt, or said they felt. But she and Nel had always seen through them. (Morrison 125)<br />
Morrison’s vivid description of Sula’s state of mind forces the reader to try and empathize with Sula, and leads the reader to question their initial reactions to social taboos. When Sula sleeps with Jude, the natural reaction of most people would be shock or disgust, and perhaps some sort of morbid curiosity as to why Sula does this. This curiosity in reading about the whys in <em>Sula</em> draws out in the reader is what compels the reader to keep reading. Taking advantage of a reader’s morbid curiosity in this way is only possible with the careful characterization that is necessary to create a realistic character that lacks certain key human traits, but still is possible to empathize with. The reason that <em>Sula</em> is a joy to read is because of this command of the characters within it.<br />
Some might say that <em>Sula</em> is an unsuccessful story because the main character is completely and utterly alien to the reader. Sula’s actions throughout the book alienate the reader from her, and it is difficult to form any sort of attachment to her because of her bizarreness. In the passage where her personality is described, Morrison describes Sula as someone who, “in the midst of a pleasant conversation with someone [might] say, ‘Why do you chew with your mouth open?’ not because the answer interested her but because she wanted to see the person’s face change rapidly. She was completely free of ambition, with no affection for money, property or things, no greed, no desire to command attention or compliments—no ego. For that reason she felt no compulsion to verify herself—be consistent with herself” (Morrison 125). Sula’s inability to conform to transactional norms makes her a more difficult character to relate to for a reader. Going by the idea that what makes a story compelling is the depth of the characterization, Sula’s weird behavior shows a lack of good characterization, and therefore is the reason the story is unsuccessful. However, while Sula’s character does have a certain alienating factor, I would argue that the blend between the parts of her personality that are impossible to relate to and the more relatable emotions that she shows in certain passages are what makes her character so compelling. In a later passage, it is said that Sula “went to bed with men as frequently as she could. It was the only place where she could find what she was looking for: misery and the ability to feel deep sorrow. She had not always been aware that it was sadness that she yearned for” (Toni Morrison 128). The specifically identified feelings of misery and sorrow when contrasted with the difficult to empathize goal of seeking this misery gives the reader the ability to understand Sula more completely, through this complex and two-pronged characterization.<br />
In sum, <em>Sula</em> succeeds in telling a compelling story because of the strength of its characters. Through looking at Sula and Jude’s desires and inner feelings, we have found that their characters are successful in different ways: Jude, because he has relatable motivations, and Sula, because her actions contrast the relatable and alien. The characterization on display in <em>Sula</em> is a prime example of how literature that aims to transport their readers should design their characters. Having more characters like Sula would make the literary world emotionally richer. <em>Sula</em> shows us characterization done right, and keeps us thinking of other perspectives.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The kind of books that stick with people are the compelling ones. For a story to command its reader’s attention and become a fond memory, it needs to tell a story with characters that feel alive. A book that is considered successful, with characters that function in this way can be said to have good characterization. Successful characterization in fiction can make the reading experience a personal one. To the individual, literature that becomes successful like this can turn into a portal into any time, and the individual can embed themselves into a fictional world. Stories like Wonder and Moby have this ability, they let the individual experience the story alongside the characters through their vivid depictions. Sula follows the life of Sula Peace, a girl who lives with her mother, grandmother, and several adopted family members in The Bottom, a relatively poor neighborhood. The story takes the reader through the life of her and some of the other members of The Bottom, eventually culminating in Sula’s staunchly different worldview leading her to become alienated from her community, and ending in her death. The rich characterization of the characters in Sula, whether they are Sula herself or other less prominent characters such as Jude, is what makes the story successful. In Sula, the character of Jude is part of what makes the book successful because of how relatable his yearning for purpose and meaningful work is. Jude works as a hotel waiter, but he craves meaningful work, and a legacy. In a passage where he has the chance to work on building a bridge, he reveals his motivations: “Jude himself longed more than anybody else to be taken. Not just for the good money, more for the work itself… His arms ached for something heavier than trays, for something dirtier than peelings; his feet wanted the heavy work shoes, not the thin-soled black shoes that the hotel required” (Morrison 92). Jude has a desire to do something other than the job he sustains himself with. The dissatisfaction with his hotel job that he feels is a common experience to a lot of people, and this desire he has makes him relatable to the reader. Jude also expresses a desire to have accomplished something that lasts long after he is gone, and this want for a legacy is also potentially relatable at the personal level to many readers, which is likely to interest readers. Jude feels that, “More than anything he wanted the camaraderie of the road men: the lunch buckets, the hollering, the body movement that in the end produced something real, something he could point to. “I built that road,” he could say. How much better sundown would be than the end of a day in the restaurant, where a good day’s work was marked by the number of dirty plates and the weight of the garbage bin. “I built that road.” People would walk over his sweat for years” (Morrison 92). Speaking for myself at least, I think that I share Jude’s desire to put something into the world that people can benefit from for many years to come. The reason that Jude’s motivations and desires are the sort that can be found in people in general is due to precise and insightful characterization, and this is why Sula is a memorable and successful piece of literature. The characterization of the title character of the story, Sula, is a key element in making the book the work of art that it is. The starkly alien perspective that Sula is shown to hold forces the reader to attempt putting themselves in Sula’s shoes, and to try and understand this strange person’s actions. Towards the end of the story, this perspective is shown: She had no thought at all of causing Nel pain when she bedded down with Jude. They had always shared the affection of other people: compared how a boy kissed, what line he used with one and then the other. Marriage, apparently, had changed all that, but having had no intimate knowledge of marriage, having lived in a house with women who thought all men available, and selected from among them with a care only for their tastes, she was ill prepared for the possessiveness of the one person she felt close to. She knew well enough what other women said and felt, or said they felt. But she and Nel had always seen through them. (Morrison 125) Morrison’s vivid description of Sula’s state of mind forces the reader to try and empathize with Sula, and leads the reader to question their initial reactions to social taboos. When Sula sleeps with Jude, the natural reaction of most people would be shock or disgust, and perhaps some sort of morbid curiosity as to why Sula does this. This curiosity in reading about the whys in Sula draws out in the reader is what compels the reader to keep reading. Taking advantage of a reader’s morbid curiosity in this way is only possible with the careful characterization that is necessary to create a realistic character that lacks certain key human traits, but still is possible to empathize with. The reason that Sula is a joy to read is because of this command of the characters within it. Some might say that Sula is an unsuccessful story because the main character is completely and utterly alien to the reader. Sula’s actions throughout the book alienate the reader from her, and it is difficult to form any sort of attachment to her because of her bizarreness. In the passage where her personality is described, Morrison describes Sula as someone who, “in the midst of a pleasant conversation with someone [might] say, ‘Why do you chew with your mouth open?’ not because the answer interested her but because she wanted to see the person’s face change rapidly. She was completely free of ambition, with no affection for money, property or things, no greed, no desire to command attention or compliments—no ego. For that reason she felt no compulsion to verify herself—be consistent with herself” (Morrison 125). Sula’s inability to conform to transactional norms makes her a more difficult character to relate to for a reader. Going by the idea that what makes a story compelling is the depth of the characterization, Sula’s weird behavior shows a lack of good characterization, and therefore is the reason the story is unsuccessful. However, while Sula’s character does have a certain alienating factor, I would argue that the blend between the parts of her personality that are impossible to relate to and the more relatable emotions that she shows in certain passages are what makes her character so compelling. In a later passage, it is said that Sula “went to bed with men as frequently as she could. It was the only place where she could find what she was looking for: misery and the ability to feel deep sorrow. She had not always been aware that it was sadness that she yearned for” (Toni Morrison 128). The specifically identified feelings of misery and sorrow when contrasted with the difficult to empathize goal of seeking this misery gives the reader the ability to understand Sula more completely, through this complex and two-pronged characterization. In sum, Sula succeeds in telling a compelling story because of the strength of its characters. Through looking at Sula and Jude’s desires and inner feelings, we have found that their characters are successful in different ways: Jude, because he has relatable motivations, and Sula, because her actions contrast the relatable and alien. The characterization on display in Sula is a prime example of how literature that aims to transport their readers should design their characters. Having more characters like Sula would make the literary world emotionally richer. Sula shows us characterization done right, and keeps us thinking of other perspectives.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Search for Meaning in Hua Hsu’s ‘Stay True’</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Meaning-in-Hua-Hsu's-'Stay-True'.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Search for Meaning in Hua Hsu’s ‘Stay True’" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Meaning-in-Hua-Hsu&apos;s-&apos;Stay-True&apos;</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Meaning-in-Hua-Hsu&apos;s-&apos;Stay-True&apos;.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Stay True</em>, is a memoir that follows the life of Hua Hsu, an award-winning writer. It begins with Hua starting at university, where most of the memoir takes place. He has a small group of close friends, the closest of which is Ken, another student who Hua initially is cold towards. During the later half of the memoir, Ken is killed in a carjacking, and Hua is shaken. He writes in a journal, intended to be read by Ken. Hua has been struggling with his identity throughout his journey, and this makes his struggle much worse. One prominent theme in <em>Stay True</em> is how alienation can affect how individuals in a community see themselves, by which I mean how people can feel alone and can lose touch with who they are in new environments where they do not feel at home. In Stay True, Hua’s journey in finding an identity that makes him feel like he is part of his community represents how individuals can struggle to find a sense of self when they are alienated, and in the wake of trauma.<br />
Hua seeks belonging, he frequently changes his traits, and this is a way that he tries to make himself more appealing to other people, and this represents how the alienated individual whittles at their identity to try and belong. In the first part of the book, when Hsu reflects on his experience in high school, he says, “I began making a zine because I’d heard it was an easy way to get free CDs from bands and record labels. But it was also a way to find a tribe. My worldview was defined by music. I cultivated a pose that was modest and small, sensitive and sarcastic, skeptical yet secretly passionate”. What this means is that Hua has a desire to be liked, and he is putting on an image of the person that he thinks people will like, instead of who he truly is. Hua’s desire to be accepted reflects how alienated individuals feel, and how their desire to be accepted drives them to artificially shape their personalities.<br />
Hua finds identity from his relationships with other people, and he defines who he is in relation to these people. This hurts him proportionally more when he loses people, and his identity is shaken as a result. This represents how when alienated individuals meld their identities to other people to fit into their communities, they can lose touch with who they are. Near the end of the book, Hua has a conversation with Gwen, one of the members of their friend group, where she questions how close Hua and Ken were. This leads Hua to doubt his friendship with Ken, as he says, “What she said cast a pall over my memories, my ability to tell a story about myself.” A major part of how Hua has defined himself was his friendship with Ken. After the loss of Ken, Hua is already having a bad time, but when his friendship with Ken is called into question, it makes him realize that he isn’t sure who he really is. He can’t define himself without Ken. This reflects how when people tie their identities to the people they care about, loss can lead them to become unsure of who they really are.<br />
	The process of healing that Hua undergoes in the last part of the book is because he learns to form an independent identity based on who he is, rather than who he thinks people will like. This represents how when individuals come to terms with who they are, and can define themselves in a vacuum, they can find happiness. Hua comes to realize who he is in the last part of the book, when he writes his second-last journal to Ken, “<em>I was actually happy today,</em> I wrote in my journal that spring. <em>I mean bullshit happy, that lighthearted feeling of carefree dizziness</em>. The impetus for joy was a slick play during a Cal basketball game. <em>I really hope you can read this. I don’t care if you can see through me</em>, I wrote, confessing to a list of imperfections and insecurities. <em>Just as long as you can see me.</em>” Hua is finally coming into his identity. Hua has found who he is, and is able to say that he can see who he is, and so can everyone else. He has realized that the person he thinks he is, is what matters. This shows how when individuals who lose touch with who they are, figure out their identity, they can achieve fulfillment.<br />
Hua has grappled with his identity throughout his life, and has been trying hard to find out who he is. The final realization that let him figure out how he could live with himself, and for himself granted him happiness. Stay True is a story about searching for identity, and how it can be a struggle to find it, but when we do, we are all the better for it. Few of us can accept the person we think we are, but in journeying to find out, we could discover that person we want to become, was the one that was inside us all along.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Stay True, is a memoir that follows the life of Hua Hsu, an award-winning writer. It begins with Hua starting at university, where most of the memoir takes place. He has a small group of close friends, the closest of which is Ken, another student who Hua initially is cold towards. During the later half of the memoir, Ken is killed in a carjacking, and Hua is shaken. He writes in a journal, intended to be read by Ken. Hua has been struggling with his identity throughout his journey, and this makes his struggle much worse. One prominent theme in Stay True is how alienation can affect how individuals in a community see themselves, by which I mean how people can feel alone and can lose touch with who they are in new environments where they do not feel at home. In Stay True, Hua’s journey in finding an identity that makes him feel like he is part of his community represents how individuals can struggle to find a sense of self when they are alienated, and in the wake of trauma. Hua seeks belonging, he frequently changes his traits, and this is a way that he tries to make himself more appealing to other people, and this represents how the alienated individual whittles at their identity to try and belong. In the first part of the book, when Hsu reflects on his experience in high school, he says, “I began making a zine because I’d heard it was an easy way to get free CDs from bands and record labels. But it was also a way to find a tribe. My worldview was defined by music. I cultivated a pose that was modest and small, sensitive and sarcastic, skeptical yet secretly passionate”. What this means is that Hua has a desire to be liked, and he is putting on an image of the person that he thinks people will like, instead of who he truly is. Hua’s desire to be accepted reflects how alienated individuals feel, and how their desire to be accepted drives them to artificially shape their personalities. Hua finds identity from his relationships with other people, and he defines who he is in relation to these people. This hurts him proportionally more when he loses people, and his identity is shaken as a result. This represents how when alienated individuals meld their identities to other people to fit into their communities, they can lose touch with who they are. Near the end of the book, Hua has a conversation with Gwen, one of the members of their friend group, where she questions how close Hua and Ken were. This leads Hua to doubt his friendship with Ken, as he says, “What she said cast a pall over my memories, my ability to tell a story about myself.” A major part of how Hua has defined himself was his friendship with Ken. After the loss of Ken, Hua is already having a bad time, but when his friendship with Ken is called into question, it makes him realize that he isn’t sure who he really is. He can’t define himself without Ken. This reflects how when people tie their identities to the people they care about, loss can lead them to become unsure of who they really are. The process of healing that Hua undergoes in the last part of the book is because he learns to form an independent identity based on who he is, rather than who he thinks people will like. This represents how when individuals come to terms with who they are, and can define themselves in a vacuum, they can find happiness. Hua comes to realize who he is in the last part of the book, when he writes his second-last journal to Ken, “I was actually happy today, I wrote in my journal that spring. I mean bullshit happy, that lighthearted feeling of carefree dizziness. The impetus for joy was a slick play during a Cal basketball game. I really hope you can read this. I don’t care if you can see through me, I wrote, confessing to a list of imperfections and insecurities. Just as long as you can see me.” Hua is finally coming into his identity. Hua has found who he is, and is able to say that he can see who he is, and so can everyone else. He has realized that the person he thinks he is, is what matters. This shows how when individuals who lose touch with who they are, figure out their identity, they can achieve fulfillment. Hua has grappled with his identity throughout his life, and has been trying hard to find out who he is. The final realization that let him figure out how he could live with himself, and for himself granted him happiness. Stay True is a story about searching for identity, and how it can be a struggle to find it, but when we do, we are all the better for it. Few of us can accept the person we think we are, but in journeying to find out, we could discover that person we want to become, was the one that was inside us all along.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Search for Purpose in The Alchemist &amp;amp; Ivan Ilyich</title><link href="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Purpose-in-The-Alchemist-&-Ivan-Ilyich.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Search for Purpose in The Alchemist &amp;amp; Ivan Ilyich" /><published>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T22:51:09-08:00</updated><id>https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Purpose-in-The-Alchemist-&amp;-Ivan-Ilyich</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://marcusjacob.me/humanities/2024/01/01/The-Search-for-Purpose-in-The-Alchemist-&amp;-Ivan-Ilyich.html"><![CDATA[<p>The search for meaning in one’s life is a journey that is core to the human experience. As long as we know, people have looked for purpose: A way to find meaning in the way we live our lives. We find happiness in this meaning, which is why we desire it. This happiness sourced from purpose is one that is not fleeting, and is deeply rooted in human nature. In Leo Tolstoy’s short story “Death of Ivan Ilyich,” Ivan Ilyich, the main character, provides some crucial insight into purpose and happiness. The story is about the life of Ivan Ilyich, who worked in a court during the tsarist regime, and his struggle with his approaching death. He has several introspections during this experience, and thinks about what he has accomplished in his life and why he has taken this path. Another story that contains crucial insights about the search for meaning and happiness is “The Alchemist” by Paulo Coelho. Its main character Santiago is a shepherd who has a dream that speaks of a treasure in a far-away land, which gives him the motivation to satisfy his desire to travel, and discovers his “personal legend,” or purpose along the way. He finds his treasure in his homeland, the true treasure being his growth and purpose that he has found through his travels. Leo Tolstoy and Paulo Coehlo are some of the most widely known authors in the world, and their insights on human nature through their books play no small part in that. These stories share the common theme of uncovering purpose, and with it, happiness. “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist” show that purpose in life is deeply connected with personal happiness, as shown through the life experiences of Ivan Ilyich and Santiago.<br />
	In “The Death of Ivan Ilyich”, Ivan Ilyich shows how lacking purpose deprives the individual of happiness. Ivan Ilyich illustrates this during his reflections on his life, where he questions his life’s accomplishments and values. On his deathbed, Ivan Ilyich questions his purpose, which shows how lacking purpose deprives oneself of happiness. This is especially true in the passages where he becomes more sure that he is going to die: “In them he saw himself and all he had lived by, and he could clearly see that it was all wrong; it was all a gross deception obscuring life and death” (Tolstoy 214). Ivan Ilyich’s impending death gives him the clarity to think about his life experiences from a more outside lens, and he finds that he does not like what he sees. He questions the achievements he held so dear through his life, the high station he prided himself on, and why he did any of this. This indicates that Ivan Ilyich went through his life lacking purpose, and never was able to grasp at happiness. His story shows how individuals can live hollow lives, lacking any real happiness, and the pain that this can cause.<br />
	In “The Alchemist”, Santiago’s journey where he follows his dreams and becomes happy in the process shows that the finding of purpose leads to happiness. Santiago reflects on his journey throughout the book:<br />
“Every second of the search is an encounter with God…When I have been truly searching for my treasure, every day has been luminous, because I’ve known that every hour was a part of the dream that I would find it. When I have been truly searching for my treasure, I’ve discovered things along the way that I never would have seen had I not had the courage to try things that seemed impossible for a shepherd to achieve” (Coelho 104).<br />
Santiago expresses here how beautifully different his life has become in the pursuit of his dream, in ways that he could never expect. He feels joy in his journey, and this represents how any individual can become happy through true purpose. Santiago also explores how this happiness lacks conditions: “It said that all people who are happy have God within them. And that happiness could be found in a grain of sand from the desert…” (Coelho 105). Here, Santiago is explicitly laying out how this happiness that is found in purpose is entirely self-sufficient, these people that have “God within them”, the people who search for purpose, find the joy in living with little to no further needs: the journey is all that we need to drive us. Santiago models how the individual’s search for meaning is intertwined with the attainment of true happiness. <br />
These stories inform us about how purpose brings us joy in life in different ways. Ivan Ilyich’s life acts as a cautionary tale that shows a life that doesn’t really seem all that bad toward the beginning, but careens toward crisis when Ivan calls the purpose of his life into question. Ivan Ilyich lived almost entirely for the pursuit of appearances, he enjoyed exercising benevolence in the use of his power to feel more superior, and from hosting parties to reading books, acted with what people thought in the forefront of his mind. Ivan Ilyich could not find purpose because he has never questioned the meaning of his life. His lack of strong purpose robbed him of satisfaction in his life choices. Santiago’s story is a more positive, but more abstract one. His total upheaval of his life leads him to find bliss, but his choice to abandon his old life is not as easy to empathize with as Ivan Ilyich’s. He differs from Ivan Ilyich because he begins by questioning the meaning of his life, and takes concrete steps to find purpose once he realizes he lacks it. He finds purpose in his travels, and lives for the pursuit of his dreams, which allows him to be happy with his life choices. What both stories tell us about purpose and its relationship to happiness is that purpose is a catalyst for true happiness. Ivan Ilyich’s story shows us how a man without purpose cannot be happy, and Santiago’s tells us how the pursuit of purpose can provide profound happiness in of itself.<br />
In sum, both “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist” explore the common theme of an individual’s search for meaning, and they model how purpose is tied to happiness, in that having purpose gives us a chance to attain lasting happiness while a lack of purpose leads to misery caused by dissatisfaction with one’s life. Today, as many members of society work jobs where we are increasingly detached from the outcomes of our work, and we so rarely can see what our work does for anyone, it can be hard to think of our lives as intrinsically purposeful. Less and less people report that they are satisfied with their lives. “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist’’ call attention to the role of purpose in our lives, and we can learn from how having or lacking meaning is shown to affect people. Even if we find it hard to directly find purpose in what we do, we could think about what we do work for as another motivator. Many of us work to provide for people, or if not, to provide for ourselves. We can look toward the people in our lives that we are there to help for purpose in the everyday. Supporting someone you care about can be something that you can look back on at the end of your life with pride, and never be in Ivan Ilyich’s position. Being the one to care for yourself is also another way to motivate yourself. Letting yourself grow can also bring meaning into your life. Santiago has shown us that being able to find something that you love doing can bring meaning into a job used to support a passion, a job that could otherwise feel dull and lifeless.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Humanities" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The search for meaning in one’s life is a journey that is core to the human experience. As long as we know, people have looked for purpose: A way to find meaning in the way we live our lives. We find happiness in this meaning, which is why we desire it. This happiness sourced from purpose is one that is not fleeting, and is deeply rooted in human nature. In Leo Tolstoy’s short story “Death of Ivan Ilyich,” Ivan Ilyich, the main character, provides some crucial insight into purpose and happiness. The story is about the life of Ivan Ilyich, who worked in a court during the tsarist regime, and his struggle with his approaching death. He has several introspections during this experience, and thinks about what he has accomplished in his life and why he has taken this path. Another story that contains crucial insights about the search for meaning and happiness is “The Alchemist” by Paulo Coelho. Its main character Santiago is a shepherd who has a dream that speaks of a treasure in a far-away land, which gives him the motivation to satisfy his desire to travel, and discovers his “personal legend,” or purpose along the way. He finds his treasure in his homeland, the true treasure being his growth and purpose that he has found through his travels. Leo Tolstoy and Paulo Coehlo are some of the most widely known authors in the world, and their insights on human nature through their books play no small part in that. These stories share the common theme of uncovering purpose, and with it, happiness. “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist” show that purpose in life is deeply connected with personal happiness, as shown through the life experiences of Ivan Ilyich and Santiago. In “The Death of Ivan Ilyich”, Ivan Ilyich shows how lacking purpose deprives the individual of happiness. Ivan Ilyich illustrates this during his reflections on his life, where he questions his life’s accomplishments and values. On his deathbed, Ivan Ilyich questions his purpose, which shows how lacking purpose deprives oneself of happiness. This is especially true in the passages where he becomes more sure that he is going to die: “In them he saw himself and all he had lived by, and he could clearly see that it was all wrong; it was all a gross deception obscuring life and death” (Tolstoy 214). Ivan Ilyich’s impending death gives him the clarity to think about his life experiences from a more outside lens, and he finds that he does not like what he sees. He questions the achievements he held so dear through his life, the high station he prided himself on, and why he did any of this. This indicates that Ivan Ilyich went through his life lacking purpose, and never was able to grasp at happiness. His story shows how individuals can live hollow lives, lacking any real happiness, and the pain that this can cause. In “The Alchemist”, Santiago’s journey where he follows his dreams and becomes happy in the process shows that the finding of purpose leads to happiness. Santiago reflects on his journey throughout the book: “Every second of the search is an encounter with God…When I have been truly searching for my treasure, every day has been luminous, because I’ve known that every hour was a part of the dream that I would find it. When I have been truly searching for my treasure, I’ve discovered things along the way that I never would have seen had I not had the courage to try things that seemed impossible for a shepherd to achieve” (Coelho 104). Santiago expresses here how beautifully different his life has become in the pursuit of his dream, in ways that he could never expect. He feels joy in his journey, and this represents how any individual can become happy through true purpose. Santiago also explores how this happiness lacks conditions: “It said that all people who are happy have God within them. And that happiness could be found in a grain of sand from the desert…” (Coelho 105). Here, Santiago is explicitly laying out how this happiness that is found in purpose is entirely self-sufficient, these people that have “God within them”, the people who search for purpose, find the joy in living with little to no further needs: the journey is all that we need to drive us. Santiago models how the individual’s search for meaning is intertwined with the attainment of true happiness. These stories inform us about how purpose brings us joy in life in different ways. Ivan Ilyich’s life acts as a cautionary tale that shows a life that doesn’t really seem all that bad toward the beginning, but careens toward crisis when Ivan calls the purpose of his life into question. Ivan Ilyich lived almost entirely for the pursuit of appearances, he enjoyed exercising benevolence in the use of his power to feel more superior, and from hosting parties to reading books, acted with what people thought in the forefront of his mind. Ivan Ilyich could not find purpose because he has never questioned the meaning of his life. His lack of strong purpose robbed him of satisfaction in his life choices. Santiago’s story is a more positive, but more abstract one. His total upheaval of his life leads him to find bliss, but his choice to abandon his old life is not as easy to empathize with as Ivan Ilyich’s. He differs from Ivan Ilyich because he begins by questioning the meaning of his life, and takes concrete steps to find purpose once he realizes he lacks it. He finds purpose in his travels, and lives for the pursuit of his dreams, which allows him to be happy with his life choices. What both stories tell us about purpose and its relationship to happiness is that purpose is a catalyst for true happiness. Ivan Ilyich’s story shows us how a man without purpose cannot be happy, and Santiago’s tells us how the pursuit of purpose can provide profound happiness in of itself. In sum, both “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist” explore the common theme of an individual’s search for meaning, and they model how purpose is tied to happiness, in that having purpose gives us a chance to attain lasting happiness while a lack of purpose leads to misery caused by dissatisfaction with one’s life. Today, as many members of society work jobs where we are increasingly detached from the outcomes of our work, and we so rarely can see what our work does for anyone, it can be hard to think of our lives as intrinsically purposeful. Less and less people report that they are satisfied with their lives. “The Death of Ivan Ilyich” and “The Alchemist’’ call attention to the role of purpose in our lives, and we can learn from how having or lacking meaning is shown to affect people. Even if we find it hard to directly find purpose in what we do, we could think about what we do work for as another motivator. Many of us work to provide for people, or if not, to provide for ourselves. We can look toward the people in our lives that we are there to help for purpose in the everyday. Supporting someone you care about can be something that you can look back on at the end of your life with pride, and never be in Ivan Ilyich’s position. Being the one to care for yourself is also another way to motivate yourself. Letting yourself grow can also bring meaning into your life. Santiago has shown us that being able to find something that you love doing can bring meaning into a job used to support a passion, a job that could otherwise feel dull and lifeless.]]></summary></entry></feed>